A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, Alfred E. Mirsky Christmas Lectures, Tapes FA876
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, Alfred E. Mirsky Christmas Lectures, Tapes
1959-2001
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA876
8.4 Cubic Feet 7 boxes.
7 boxes.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 600-5.
Arrangement
Chronological
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for scholarly research.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Vivisection; Genetics; DNA; Biology -- Research; Medicine, Preventive; Medical care; China; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medical research; Medical sciences; Seitz, Frederick; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; MacLeod, Colin M. (Colin Munro); Avery, Oswald Theodore; McCarty, Maclyn; Rockefeller University
- Christmas lectures, 1968-1989; 5 inch boxes. Tapes are 7 inch reels
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also: Alfred E. Mirsky papers
  Biographical/Historical note
  The Christmas Lectures were started at The Rockefeller University in 1959 under the guidance of Alfred E. Mirsky. For a complete history see the Alfred E. Mirsky papers. After Dr. Mirsky's death in June 1974 the lectures were renamed The Alfred E. Mirsky Christmas Lectures on Science.
  The taping of the Christmas Lectures began in 1968. Originally they were taped, numbered and stored consecutively with other taped University events. Since 1972 Christmas Lecture tapes are handled as an individual series. In the Archives, starting with the 1968 tapes, the series is kept as a discreet unit. A very few of the earliest lectures can be found with the papers of the scientist who delivered the lecture. Catalog card descriptions should bring together all those that are available in the archives.
  1959-1975
  1959 René Dubos: The Unseen World
  1960 Paul Weiss: Living Forms
  1961 Lyman Craig, Stanford Moore, William Stein: On Separating Things
  1962 Mark Kac: Chance and Regularity
  1963 Sam Goudsmit: Light and Quanta
  1964 James Hirsch: White Cells
  1965 Alfred E. Mirsky, Vincent G. Allfrey: The Cell Nucleus
  1966 Donald Griffin: Animal Navigation and Communication
  1967 Peter Marler: Social Behavior of Monkevs and Apes
  1968 Igor Tamm, Purnell Choppin: Viruses In and Out of Cells
  1969 No lecture
  1970 James Hirsch, Zanvil Cohn: White Cells
  1971 Vincent Dole: Drug Addiction
  1972 Roger Payne: Whales
  1973 Bruce McEwen: Hormones and the Brain
  1974 Armin C. Braun: An Introduction to the Biology of Cancer
  1975 Floyd Ratliff: Vision and the Retina
  Scope and Contents note
  Addition to 1982 AEM Christmas Lectures on Science: [21 Apr 1986. Received from S.W. Mirsky. Joel E. Cohen.* An Uncertainty Principle in Demography and the Unisex Issue." American Statistician 40 (1986 Feb) 32-39. Reprint. *...Previous versions of this work were presented in the 1982 Alfred E. Mirsky Lectures in [should be 'on'] Science at Rockefeller University..." w/handwritten note attached by Joel Cohen/Sonya W. Mirsky, 13 April 1986].
  Custodial History note
  Received 1974 and later.
  Conditions Governing Access
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  - VIRUSES IN AND OUT OF CELLS, 28-29 December 1968 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6929)
    Choppin, Purnell W.; Tamm, I. E. (Igor Evgenevich)
  - WHITE CELLS, 29 December 1970 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6926)
    Cohn, Zanvil
  - DRUG ADDICTION I, 27 December 1971 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6927)
    Dole, Vincent
  - DRUG ADDICTION II, 28 December 1971 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6928)
  - WHALES I, 27 December 1972 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6930)
    Payne, Roger, 1935-
  - WHALES II, 27 December 1972 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6931)
  - WHALES III, 28 December 1972 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6932)
  - WHALES IV, 28 December 1972 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6933)
  - ROGER PAYNE, 1972 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6919)
  - HORMONES AND THE BRAIN I, 27-28 December 1973 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6920)
    McEwen, Bruce S.
  - HORMONES AND THE BRAIN II, 27-28 December 1973 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6921)
  - AN INTRODUCTION TO THE BIOLOGY OF CANCER I, 30 December 1974 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6924)
    Braun, Armin C.
  - AN INTRODUCTION TO THE BIOLOGY OF CANCER II, 31 December 1974 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6925)
  - VISION AND THE RETINA I, 29 December 1975 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6922)
    Ratliff, Floyd
  - VISION AND THE RETINA II, 29 December 1975 (Box 1, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6923)
  - VISION AND THE RETINA III, 30 December 1975 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6902)
  - VISION AND THE RETINA IV, 30 December 1975 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6903)
  - A GUIDED TOUR OF THE LIVING CELL I, 27 December 1976 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6916)
    De Duve, Christian
  - A GUIDED TOUR OF THE LIVING CELL II, 28 December 1976 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6915)
  - THE VERBAL MACHINERY OF THINKING I, 27 December 1977 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6917)
    Scope and Contents
    An error was made in the taping of this program. Only the question and answer period was taped. Complete transcript of the lecture is available.
    Miller, George E.
  - THE VERBAL MACHINERY OF THINKING II, 28 December 1977 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6918)
  - MOLECULES IN MOTION: THE KINETIC THEORY OF MATTER I, 27 December 1978 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6912)
    Cohen, E.D.G., Dr.
  - MOLECULES IN MOTION: THE KINETIC THEORY OF MATTER II, 27 December 1978 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6909)
  - MOLECULES IN MOTION: THE KINETIC THEORY OF MATTER III, 28 December 1978 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6910)
  - MOLECULES IN MOTION: THE KINETIC THEORY OF MATTER IV, 28 December 1978 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6911)
  - BIOCHEMICAL HORIZONS WITH A FOCUS ON PROTEIN CHEMISTRY I, 29-30 December 1980 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6913)
    Moore, Stanford
  - BIOCHEMICAL HORIZONS WITH A FOCUS ON PROTEIN CHEMISTRY II, 29-30 December 1980 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6914)
  - WHITE BLOOD CELLS I, 29 December 1981 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6905)
    Lecture 1: Their structure. Lecture 2: How they eat and drink
    Silverstein, Samuel C.
  - WHITE BLOOD CELLS II, 30 December 1981 (Box 2, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6904)
    Lecture 3: Defense against microbes and tumors. Lecture 4: Legionnaires disease.
  - BRAINS I, 28 December 1983 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6906)
    Lecture 1. Learning to Sing - Birdsong as a complex motor skill. Lecture 2. Two Brains in One - Functions of the two hemispheres and the riddle of consciousness.
    Nottebohm, Fernando
  - BRAINS II, 29 December 1983 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6907)
    Lecture 3. Sex and the Brain - Male and brains show interesting anatomical differences.
  - BRAINS III, 29 December 1983 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6908)
    Lecture 4. Replaceable Neurons - Some types of adult brain neurons are constantly replaced by other neurons born in adulthood.
  - THE ECOLOGY AND MOLECULAR BIOLOGY OF BACTERIAL DISEASES I, 26 December 1984 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6939)
    Lecture 1 and 2.
    Gotschlich, Emil C.
  - THE ECOLOGY AND MOLECULAR BIOLOGY OF BACTERIAL DISEASES I, 26 December 1984 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6953)
    Introduction by Paul F. Cranefield. Lecture 1. Bacterial Diseases - The Rules of the Game.
  - THE ECOLOGY AND MOLECULAR BIOLOGY OF BACTERIAL DISEASES II, 27 December 1984 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6940)
    Lectures 3 and 4.
  - THE ECOLOGY AND MOLECULAR BIOLOGY OF BACTERIAL DISEASES II, 26 December 1984 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6952)
    Lecture 2. Gonococcus - The Professional.
  - THE ECOLOGY AND MOLECULAR BIOLOGY OF BACTERIAL DISEASES III, 27 December 1984 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6954)
    Lecture 3. Cholera Bacillus - A Man for All Seasons
  - THE ECOLOGY AND MOLECULAR BIOLOGY OF BACTERIAL DISEASES IV, 27 December 1984 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6955)
    Lecture 4. Vaccines - Of Mice and Men.
  - SKIN: OUR PROTECTIVE ENVELOPE I, 26 December 1985 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6938)
    Carter, D. Martin (David Martin), 1936-
  - SKIN: OUR PROTECTIVE ENVELOPE I, 26 December 1985 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6943)
    Lecture 1: Barrier - How the filamentuous keratin layer of the skin controls fluid loss and drug absorption. Lecture 2: Color - How pigment cells migrate and synthesize and transfer melanin.
  - SKIN: OUR PROTECTIVE ENVELOPE II, 27 December 1985 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6937)
  - SKIN: OUR PROTECTIVE ENVELOPE II, 27 December 1985 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6942)
    Lecture 3: Healing - How the healing of wounds is enhanced by "Artificial skin" and biosynthetic dressings.
  - SKIN: OUR PROTECTIVE ENVELOPE III, 27 December 1985 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6936)
  - SKIN: OUR PROTECTIVE ENVELOPE III, 27 December 1985 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6941)
    Lecture 4: Repair - How cells repair DNA damage caused by ultraviolet, x rays, and chemicals.
  - QUARKS - THE FUNDAMENTAL CONSTITUENTS OF MATTER? I, 26 December 1986 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6935)
    Cool, Rodney L.
  - QUARKS - THE FUNDAMENTAL CONSTITUENTS OF MATTER? II, 26 December 1986 (Box 3, 1/4 inch audio tape AV 6934)
  - TAPE 4, 29 December 1987 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6946)
  - ENZYMES - STRUCTURES, FUNCTION, DESIGN, AND CONSTRUCTION, 29 December 1987 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6947)
    Tape 2
    Kaiser, Emil Thomas
  - T-CELL MEDIATED IMMUNITY I, 1988 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6956)
    Steinman, Ralph M.
  - T-CELL MEDIATED IMMUNITY II, 1988 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6957)
  - T-CELL MEDIATED IMMUNITY III, 1988 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6958)
  - CHRISTMAS LECTURES I, 1989 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6945)
  - CHRISTMAS LECTURES II, 1989 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6948)
  - CHRISTMAS LECTURES III, 1989 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6949)
  - CHRISTMAS LECTURES IV, 1989 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6950)
  - TAPE 1 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6951)
  - TAPE 3 (1/4 inch audio cassette AV 6944)